so we already know that ILP is not equal
to ie PC on any real processor actually
it can be but it's not necessarily so
and that is because ILP is really the
IPC on a perfect processor that does
perfect branch prediction and only has
to follow data dependencies so now let's
look at an example of a program in the
real processor and see basically how do
we determine LP and how do we determine
the IPC so this is our program and now
let's look at what the processor looks
like sir processor is to issue meaning
it can handle two instructions per cycle
out-of-order superscalar which means
that it doesn't need to execute
instructions exactly in program order
and let's say that it only has one
multiplication unit and two units that
can do add two tracks X or Z etc for our
ILP we can just ignore all of this
because they LP again is just the
property of a program so we have to just
obey dependencies there is a data
dependence here and that's only really
the only dependence that we have so as
far as ILP is concerned we can do this
in two cycles this this this and this
would be done in the first cycle
and then this would be done in the
second cycle because it depends on the
instruction that is done in the first
cycle so we have five instructions over
two cycles gives us 2.5 in contrast the
IPC for this processor needs to consider
all the limitations of this processor so
we have this instruction can be done in
the first cycle this one cannot because
of a dependence so before the IPC we
still have to obey all the dependencies
plus we have to also worry about the
other limitations of the processor this
is an out-of-order processor so we are
not doing this but we can still look
further because we can do instructions
out of order the XOR can be done because
we have to add subtract etc units so we
can do this in the first cycle to this
instruction can be done in the first
cycle because we can use the multiplier
but for example this instruction here
cannot be done in the first cycle unlike
when we computed the ILP it cannot be
done because we only have to add
subtract XOR etc
and we have already consumed both of
them in the first cycle for the ad in
the expects or so in the second cycle
now we can do this and this so it turns
out that I our IPC is still five
instructions over two cycles equals to
0.5 but it doesn't have to be that way
for example if this processor only had
one add subtract X or unit we would now
have the IPC 1/2 in the first cycle we
can do this we cannot do this because of
a dependence we cannot do this because
we are already using our one unit that
we have for add taxes etc we can do the
multiply and we cannot do this at either
in the second cycle we can do this we
cannot do any of these other two because
again we are using where our add
subtract X or unit this would be in our
third cycle and this would be our fourth
cycle so now we have five instructions
over four cycles and that's equal to
1.25 so this IPC is half of this IPC and
half of this LP so what we can say is
that the IPC has to be less than or
equal to the ILP the ILP is for a
perfect processor a real processor will
have some limitations that will maybe
allow it to achieve the same IPC as the
ILP available in the application but
sometimes it will not so what we can say
is that the ILP is always greater than
or equal to the IPC on any real
processor and again we didn't really
need to know what the processor is to
compute the LP but we do need to know
what the processor looks like when we
are computing its IPC and we have seen
that the IPC can be equal to the LP or
it can be lower than that but it cannot
be larger than that